3 months back, my friend,
senior data engineer,
8 years of experience and 6 figure
salary,
called me and said,
He got laid off in a company.
But do you know what is more
shocking than that?
In the same company, in the same
position,
3 weeks later,
that position got filled with a 25
year old kid.
I mean he has literally 3 years of
experience in the industry.
But what is the difference between
him and my friend?
Do you understand?
That kid knows how to build AI
agents in real time in production
guys.
That is the world that we are
currently living in.
If you are watching this video,
there will be 3 questions in your
brain.
Will AI replace my job?
Am I too late to learn AI in 2026?
And am I still relevant without
learning agentic AI in 2026?
I will answer all of these 3
questions guys.
But by the end of this video,
I have to give a roadmap to my own
brother.
This is the video that I am going to
share with him.
But before that,
I will tell you one small warning.
90 % of the people start this
journey and quit in the first month.
I have seen so many people doing
this.
I will tell you why in some point of
time.
There are 3 paths to enter AI in
2026 guys.
And if you pick the wrong one,
you are going to waste at least one
complete year of your time.
So please be cautious.
So let's start with the first one.
The traditional route in which you
will learn Python,
probability, statistics,
machine learning basics,
deep learning basics,
and then you do the projects,
and after doing all that,
then you start getting into LLMs.
What are LLMs?
And then what are agents?
You build all of these stuff.
So it will take at least one year of
your time guys,
if you want to learn properly.
Honestly, in 2020,
if you ask me about this roadmap or
this route,
I would say this is perfect.
But in 2026,
this is literally outdated guys.
There is no one who is going to ask
you
regarding traditional machine
learning and
traditional deep learning in AI
agentic interviews.
And then let's talk about the second
approach,
which is the hybrid approach,
where you start learning with
Python,
machine learning and deep learning,
but only basics.
Very basics.
And then within very short amount of
time,
you quickly jump into LLMs,
and you start working with LLMs,
agents, tools, MCPs,
a lot of new stuff.
So by doing this,
you might bring back that time from
one year
to maybe 8 months,
but even then you are going to spend
a lot of time.
I think this might be a good
approach,
but if you are someone who is non
-technical,
this approach will take
and will consume a lot of your
capacity guys.
So my recommendation is,
to enter AI in 2026,
this is the best approach,
which is the third approach.
You directly start with LLMs.
LLMs means ENT, how to work with
these things.
You might know what is chart GPT,
cloud code means ENT, cursor means
ENT.
You understand these tools,
and you understand how these LLMs
work.
After that, you start building
agents,
and then you start understanding
MCPs,
skills and tools.
Honestly, this is the best roadmap
right now.
So the advantage is,
you are learning the topics that
companies
are directly looking for right now.
If you open LinkedIn directly,
there are so many
jobs on AI,
AI, AI, everywhere,
agent AI mostly.
So there is a huge demand in the
jobs
regarding AI engineers
or agentic engineers,
but there are very few number of
people
who have these skills.
So there is a gap.
I want everyone to tap into that gap
to earn a huge amount of money guys,
because that is where the entire
world is heading towards.
And this is what I wanted to teach
everyone.
So I have created a detailed
roadmap
and we are going to discuss that
in the next part.
So let me answer the question that
you actually
came in for guys.
Will AI replace my job?
So to be brutally honest,
if your job is something
that is writing
basic code, maybe let's say
you are building basic dashboards,
or maybe
summarizing documents,
drafting emails, or maybe something
that is repetitive all the time,
then you can already do
these things with LLMs,
maybe
charge GPT, cloud, cursor,
all of these
can do. So if you are doing
something
that LLM can also do,
then definitely your job is
replaceable
guys. But there is a small catch.
Then who is building these LLMs?
So how are we making these
LLMs to do our tasks?
We have to build them,
right?
And when we build them,
that will
break, we have to fix them.
To connect that with the company
resources,
you need someone to orchestrate
everything.
That is the exact
role for AI engineer in 2026.
To orchestrate
every single thing, such that
you can eliminate the repetitive
tasks.
So to be precise, AI
is not replacing your job guys.
AI
is creating new jobs
that doesn't exist in the last 3
years
in the market. So there is this
huge potential and huge opportunity
that anyone can tap into,
even the non -technical person as
well.
And that is what I am going to
tell you in the next 15 or 10
minutes,
the detailed road map to become
an AI architect or AI engineer
in 2026. And by
the way, a quick intro of me for the
people who
don't know me guys. I am Balai
Chippada.
I have 8 years of experience in the
field of AI
and machine learning. I have worked
at
multiple companies and I have built
projects
which are in production right now at
a large scale.
And personally, I have mentored
more than 3000 plus students and
working
professionals to transform their
career into AI.
So maybe you are the next one.
So yeah, let's get started.
Guys,
this is the complete website
that I have built for you guys.
To become an AI engineer in 2026.
And to be honest, this is not
a normal website. I didn't
build the website by just charging
it or giving a prompt in the cloud.
I had to talk to a lot of friends
who
are working in different domains,
different
technologies and companies like
FANG and MANG and other companies
which are top based product
companies guys.
I asked them the same question.
What kind of tech stack are you
using
What are the things that you thought
would have been better if you had
learned
before? I had to take their inputs
and build this road map to become
an AI engineer in 2026 guys.
Now I am dividing that road map
into multiple steps step by step
so that you can follow without
confusion guys. And trust me
building this is not easy.
It took me
approximately one week to gather the
context and at least two days to
finalize this website.
So I want
you to use this as a single
source of truth to become
the road map for AI engineer in
2026.
So the intent behind this is
you don't need to search for 10
different places
10 different topics, how to do it,
what to do
This is going to be your
single source of truth.
Trust me on
this one. And the best thing I am
not
gatekeeping this before anything
guys.
I am not asking you to pay money.
You can find the website link
in the description below
and you can directly go ahead
and look for this one.
And one more small request from my
side
guys. Even if you don't need this
if you know someone who needs this
maybe recently lost their job and
they want
to upskill in AI in 2026
then please share this website or
please share
this video such that they can also
get
motivated and start learning all of
these topics
that we are about to cover.
And there are
couple of things that I want to talk
about this website
guys. This website has a light mode
and a dark mode.
And I am going to use light mode
to explain all the topics because it
will be easy
and if you are someone who likes
dark
mode you can do this one but I am
going to
keep it for light mode in this video
at least and you can search for
these topics
but I am not going to cover this
right now.
We divided this road map into
multiple sections
guys. Specifically 9 sections on
MATA.
So let me talk about high level what
are these sections
for. First we will learn about
Python
and then what are LLMs,
RGP TNT,
Cloud TNT, how do they work and then
prompt engineering, injection
pipelines
and RAG, tools, MCPs,
single agents, memory,
context
engineering, how to build agents,
multi
agent orchestration and then the
guard
rails and LLM ops and also the Cloud
and deployment. So if we look at
these
topics all of these topics are
needed to build a production level
agent
project in a company guys.
So this is a complete road map
that I wanted to share with you and
along with that not only topics we
will
also build a couple of projects
which will apply
all of the topics that we have
learned in this
one and as always I have my
deduction
here if you want you can follow me
on LinkedIn
YouTube and Instagram so I am always
available there and let's talk
about what are the topics and what
are we going
to cover in these sections.
So before
I explain this road map imagine
one thing guys. Let's say
there is a person. That person
has read every single thing
or every single book in the entire
internet, Wikipedia articles,
research
papers, every single knowledge
until a specific cut
off date maybe let's say January
2026. Then you take that person
and lock him in a room
that room has no windows,
no ventilation, no door,
nothing
at all. Then you ask that person
a question. What is the weather
today?
Today's weather, today
may be it's in the April 29th
then that person
doesn't know what's happening
outside
but he will confidently
guess one answer and he will
throw you that answer.
That answer
may be wrong. That is called
hallucination. Now
this person is the brain
that brain is what we call
it as large language models
Manchajipiti, Claude,
Grog, Gemini
all of these have these LLMs
which has immense
amount of knowledge that has
been trained with the internet
data till a cut off date.
In the next 6 months, how do we
communicate
with that brain?
How do we give hands and legs
to that brain? How do we
give external knowledge to that
brain?
We learn all these things.
So let's get to the road map now.
Now to talk with that brain
we need a language, right?
That language is called Python
and that is our phase 1.
It takes approximately 1 to 3 weeks
guys if you are a beginner.
If you already know these things you
can skip it
but this Python is little bit
different
to what you already know because
the Python we learn here
is the core Python and also
majorly we will cover
the object oriented programming
and also the error handling and the
file handling
and the important stuff is
working with HTTP APIs
and the fast API because
all the LLMs like ChargPT,
Cloud, Gemini
all of these
you will communicate via Python
using APIs.
How to use them, how to use those
things
everything we will learn step by
step
in detail. And the best part
is this async programming.
Async programming means
in typical Python programming
when you define a function
if you call that function,
until that function is executed
the Python will keep on
running at the same position.
But if you are using async
programming
you can call multiple functions
at every single time
and until that function is executed
Python will stop there but in the
mean time
it can execute different function
calls as well.
So we will understand how to
use that and how to build
functions using async Python
programming.
And then we move on to the second
phase
which is the mental model of
LLMs guys. In this almost
there is no piece of code.
What we will learn in this is
we have a brain right?
That is what we call it as an LLM.
What is an LLM? How do LLMs train?
How do they work?
And then how do they think?
Some LLMs are fast, some are slow.
If you notice, when you
ask a question with a charge
it will give you an answer very
instantly.
Sometimes it will think and answer.
So what is this thinking?
What is this reasoning model?
What is the react pattern?
You will learn all of these things.
Why some models are very fast?
Why some models are very slow?
How to use them? What are tokens?
What is the context window?
You get to understand
a lot of intricate details
about LLMs, the brain guys.
How to control the output of
an LLM? What is temperature?
What is creativity?
What is hallucination?
You get all of the theory with all
the
live examples in this one.
Almost there is zero code in this
section guys.
So it is not that much difficult.
If you look at the difficulty level,
it is 1 star.
And then you also compare different
models from different providers.
In charge GPT there are different
models.
O3, O4, 5.5, 5.6.
There is no 5.6.
In cloud there is 4.6,
4.7, 4.5.
So which model
you have to prefer for which kind of
tasks?
You will learn all of these things
every single detail with examples
guys.
So at the end,
you can explain to a non -technical
personal manager why charge GPT
made up a fact and tell a hiring
panel which model to pick for which
job
backed by benchmarks
and not vibes.
So this is what you will learn in
the phase 2.
And then moving on to the next phase
which is very interesting phase
which is called
prompt engineering and API access
guys.
This difficulty level is little
bit high compared to the previous
ones.
Because here in the starting
you wanted a language to talk with
the brain.
And in the second you will
understand how this brain works.
But here you will learn
to understand how you can
expect or extract the perfect
results every time when you ask
a question. If you have seen
in Instagram or Reels
copy this prompt, you will get the
output.
Do this prompt, you will get the
output. Why do you say that?
If you give a generic information
LLMs does not understand clearly.
But when you give perfect
information
that is what we call it as prompt
engineering.
You have to provide
different information for different
tasks.
That is what you are going to learn
here.
For any kind of LLM models
it could be RGPD, it could be
Claude, it could be LLM
any kind of LLM.
What are the core techniques that we
have?
And what are the applied prompt
patterns that are tested by
lot of developers? And then what are
the
advanced engineering models?
And the prompt management and also
we will understand the cost
efficiency as well. Because
whenever you are sending questions
to LLMs
you are using a lot of tokens.
And whenever you are losing a lot of
tokens
you are utilizing the money.
So how to send the prompt
our tokens will be less
and then our cost will be less
at the end of the day.
That is also
what we will learn in this phase
itself.
Do you remember the promises in the
beginning?
Why 90 % of the people
will quit in their first month?
Because of this RAG guys.
RAG and also the next phase which is
basically tools, MCPs and agents.
So that is why difficulty level is
also
4 and it will take at least 4 weeks
to learn RAG. So remember our
brain analogy. So now we have a
brain.
Now the next question is
How can I pass a couple
of documents to the brain such
that the brain can access those
documents and answer questions
from those documents? That is
what RAG is called. Which is
basically
Retrieved Augmented Generation
guys. RAG and a concept is
a very complex concept.
But many
people write RAG is very easy,
RAG is
very simple in YouTube.
And you will follow that
and you will build a streaming
application and you will go to the
interview
and the moment interviewer ask
questions regarding technical
details of RAG you will
fail. That is where motivation will
be
destroyed guys. RAG is a very
complex topic and building
applications using RAG
that scale in the production is what
a real agent TK engineer will do.
That is what I have done it.
So if you look at these steps here
first we will talk about why RAG
exists. RAG
and then when
to use RAG and when not to use RAG.
And then what are embeddings,
different types of embeddings.
And then document ingestion
pipelines, all industrial documents,
chunking strategies, different
different
strategies that we have.
And then chunking enrichment.
And then we have vector database.
What kind of
database I need to use?
Whether I need to use a local
database?
Whether I need to use an online
I mean HNSW, there are so
many techniques, so many small small
system
level details are there that makes
RAG very complex actually.
And then the next which is basically
hybrid
retrievals and next generation
retrievers.
And then the latest topic which is
called
vectorless RAG which is also called
as graph
rag guys. And then we also look
at the evaluation part.
This is where
most of your tutorials will fail to
teach.
So you have built a RAG application.
But how accurate it is in the
production?
What is the latency?
What is the truthfulness score?
What is the groundness
factor? So all of these things
nobody will teach. Why did I
prepare all this? I have talked to a
lot of
people and I have personally built
this RAG
applications and companies that
scale to
millions of people. So I know what
to do and how to do. That is what
I want to teach to every one of you
guys.
This is not a simple build road map.
And the next part
which is basically tools,
MCPs
and single agents guys.
But we have
brain. That brain gave us documents.
Now I want to give
the brain hands and legs
such that it can act on its own.
That is what we have tools
and MCPs and agents guys.
What are tools? Let's say
you have asked a question to a
charge GPT.
It answers in a specific way.
But you want
that answer to be in a different
format.
That is what tools are.
And MCPs. There is a charge GPT
UI. There is a cloud UI.
You type and you get answers.
But if you see
an option, the charge GPT or cloud
they can connect to the Google drive
or Google calendar. It can connect
to different applications like MCPs.
Like Figma.
There are so many applications guys.
Now how can you make
an LLM connect
to an application that you want.
Maybe you want to
connect your database.
How can you connect it?
Maybe you want to connect to Jira so
that you can
automate your tasks. So that is what
we call it as an MCP guys.
How can you create
an agent
that can autonomously do your
work? That is what single
agents are doing. So we will cover
every single thing. Function
calling. Tool use.
Tool descriptions. Design
principles.
MCPs. React patterns.
Using Lang chain is a framework that
will help us
to build all of these things.
And human in the
loop. Tool security. And then what
are SDKs. This is also a very
important
concept that we will touch later on.
And then we have something
called as memory and context
engineering.
There is a person who has a brain.
That brain has long term memory
guys.
You will talk and it will remember.
But it will remember
because it is where you want to
bring in
memory to the LLMs. So how can
LLMs remember what the personalized
details for you.
If you ask your question with
charge,
it will say high balance.
So how does it
remember your name? That is what we
call it
as memory. So when you are building
an application
how can you incorporate
memory? What is a short term memory?
What is a long term memory? What is
the structure?
What is the system? What is the
context?
And what is semantic caching?
And what is
episodic memory? And long term
memory
and context compression.
You will learn all of these
techniques in detail.
And then that is
where you will
build multiple agents
that coordinate with each other
and do your tasks autonomously.
Have you heard about open class?
That is what it is doing.
How can
you create multiple agents
that can do or automate your
life continuously autonomously?
This is where most people
fail guys. This is the highest
difficulty level which is difficulty
level of 5.
So how can you create it?
How can you create
Langroff? And how can you
use these things? Agent as a tool,
state
management, agent to agent protocol,
frameworks compared, debugging
multiple systems. Now they are
failing, now they are getting
correct.
So all of these things you will
learn
step by step with live examples
guys. That is what I wanted to teach
all of you on YouTube.
And then the next is the
best one which is guardrails
and LLM Ops. Many
YouTubers they will not teach you
these guys
because this is a very hard concept.
What is guardrails? If you go
and ask RGPT about suicide or
bomb, it will not tell you the
details
because those are guardrails.
It will not work in a way
that will respond in a bad manner.
You don't want to do that.
Maybe if you ask
RGPT regarding APA keys
it will not tell you APA keys
because that is the limitation.
So in this project, how can you
put your guardrails?
How can you put input guardrails?
How can you put output guardrails?
How can you eliminate
LLM injection?
Prompt injection.
So all of these things you will
learn
and you will learn how to use it in
AWS
bedrock, LLM Ops, observability
and evaluations. You will learn
every
single thing guys. How to control
the activity of your agent
based on the guardrails.
Now using all these
you built a project that is running
successfully on your local machine.
But in my local machine what is the
use of
this one? At the end of the day you
need
to deploy it somewhere.
That is where the phase 9 will come
into picture
which is the cloud infrastructure
and
deployment. We will take
one example of a cloud guys because
all the
clouds are very similar.
So we will cover
mostly on Amazon. So we will use
S3, we will use compute like
Lambda, ECS Fargate, ECR
and networking and access because
you need to
talk to APS which will cover
VPC, subnet, security groups
and then deployment, how to
calculate the cost and capacity
every single thing
regarding deployment as well.
How to measure the
latency. We will learn every
single thing step by step guys.
So by the end of phase 9 you will
be able to build multi -agent
orchestrator
which will work autonomously
based on thinking and react
patterns which will run
continuously on a cloud environment
guys.
This is what a real agent
developer will do
and this is what companies expect
you to do. And
after this you will
build three capstone projects.
One is regarding the rag and
one is regarding multi -agent
orchestration
and then everything regarding
every single topics, tools,
MCPs, rags and then putting on
cloud.
And with this
this is where you will complete your
learning for now. So what this
does not cover the fine tuning of
foundation models and voice
agents. We are not going to cover
any voice agents
guys. And ML fundamentals
gradient descent NT, back
propagation NT,
transformers NT will not cover all
of these things. Because you want
to learn as much as possible
such that you can
go and apply for the job today
and you crack it and you start
working on
the development of agent AI.
And then
we have this, we will not cover
the front end development or back
end development, nothing at all.
And then where to go from here?
So at the end of the day
you will have three projects,
you will have
the skills that will work in the
real time
and you can build your resume which
will replicate just like my resume
or maybe some others resume who is
working in man and fan companies
guys.
So the journey ends
here where the real work begins.
So this is what I want to teach
every
single thing in YouTube for free of
cost.
So if you know someone
who wants this or who needs
this, please share it with them.
And if you update your link,
you will
get in the description. I am not
gatekeeping anything.
And if you like the content and
the delivery, please comment it
whatever you feel like.
That will
show me
some love and I will be motivated to
do this
regularly. So this is an
opportunity that is open right now
and it might not be open in 2028
guys. So if you know someone
or if you know someone who wants it
or needs it, please share it.
I am asking you
once again because maybe someone
will get benefited from this video.
So without any delay,
let's start building and let's meet
in the next session or next video.
Bye bye.